Guide to the Willi Bredel Papers, 1950-1976
Department of Special Collections
Bredel, Willi, 1901-1964. Papers,
1950-1976
M0665
Bredel, Willi, 1901-1964
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased from Antiquariat Magister Tinius, Berlin, 1993.
Biography
A socialist writer known for his depictions of proletarian life, Bredel was born in Hamburg. He joined the Communist Party at eighteen. In 1928 he became editor of HAMBURGER VOLKSZEITUNG, and two years later he was sentenced to a two-year jail term for "planning literary high treason." During this period he wrote his first novel, MASCHINENFABRIK N & K. Bredel was imprisoned by the Nazis from 1933 to 1934, and when released fled to Moscow, where he was one of the original founders of the "Nationalkomittee 'Freies Deutschland'" in 1943. After the war, Bredel settled in East Germany. He served as the editor of HEUTE UND MORGEN (1947-1954) and NEUE DEUTSCHE LITERATUR (1953-1956). From 1956 unti his death in 1964, Bredel was a member of the Central Committee of the East German Communist Party.
Scope and Content
The papers come from Bredel's secretary, Ursula Kilian, who worked for him from 1953 to 1964. Included are Bredel's notes to Kilian, as well as some carbon copies of her letters to him; Bredel's correspondence with others including Walter Janka and Friedrich Ebert; one letter from Bredel to Walter Ulbricht complaining that the paper allotment for his magazine had been suddenly cancelled; and a few items from Maj Bredel, Willi Bredel's wife.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
. 10$aBredel, Maj.;. 10$aEbert, Friedrich, 1894-1979.;. 10$aJanka, Walter, 1914-;. 10$aKilian, Ursula.;. 10$aUlbricht, Walter, 1893-1973.;. 0$aEast European literature.;. 0$aGerman literature--20th century.;. 0$aRevolutionary literature, German.;. 0$aSocialism in literature.
Collection Contents
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1964 and exhibition invitation, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Maj Bredel-Killian correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence-- cards, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence-- cards, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence-- cards, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence-- cards, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence-- cards, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence-- cards, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence-- cards, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence-- cards, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence-- cards, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence-- cards, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Bredel-Killian correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Bredel correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Bredel correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Bredel correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Bredel correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  (includes one 3-page manuscript, "Zum internationalen Befreiungstag. Klaren Verstand- standhaften Charakter- Geduld.")
- Bredel correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Bredel correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 30)
Bibliography
Willi Bredel, Gesammelte Werke (Berlin, 1962-76).
L. Bock, Willi Bredel. Leben und Werk (Berlin, 1990).